Raoul family papers, 1865-1985
Emory University
- Letters and personal papers, 1865-1982, Series 1; Boxes 1-35, OP 1-2
  - Thomas Wadley Raoul papers, 1886-1933, Subseries 1.7; Personal name.; Box 23-23c
    Thomas Wadley Raoul's letters to his mother and other family members, particularly his father and sister Mary, cover 1886 to 1933, with the majority dating between 1895 and 1901. His early letters concern his travels to the Chicago World's Fair and Mexico, social events in Atlanta and Bolingbroke, and his employment in Macon (1895-1896). Many letters after 1896 were written during the frequent trips he undertook seeking a cure for his tuberculosis. These include letters from Mexico and California (1896-1897), Europe (1903), Arizona and Oregon (1904-1907), and Germany (1909). Several of the 1909 letters from Germany concern the condition of his sister Rosine, who contracted the disease during their stay there.
    The majority of Tom Raoul's letters were written from Asheville, where he settled for health reasons in 1897. These primarily relate to the development and operation of the Albemarle Park Company. A few printed materials about Albemarle Park are included with the letters of 1902. Other Asheville letters concern social life at the Manor, visits from architect Bradford Gilbert and from family members, and civic and community affairs, particularly the public school system, road building, the activities of the Vanderbilt family (1900), and the status of tuberculosis legislation and the hotel trade in North Carolina (1915).
    - Letters, 1886-1943
    - 1886-1892 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - 1895 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 1896 January-June (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - 1896 July - December (Box 23, Folder 4a)
    - 1897 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - 1898, January- March (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - 1898, April-December (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - 1898, January-April (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - 1899, May-December (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - 1900, January-May (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - 1900, June-December (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - 1901, January-April (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - 1901, May-August (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - 1901, September-December (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - 1902 (Box 23a, Folder 1)
    - 1903, January-April (Box 23a, Folder 2)
    - 1903, May-August (Box 23a, Folder 3)
    - 1903, September-December (Box 23a, Folder 4)
    - 1904, February-March (Box 23a, Folder 5)
    - 1904, April-June (Box 23a, Folder 6)
    - 1904, July (Box 23a, Folder 7)
    - 1904, August-September (Box 23a, Folder 8)
    - 1904, October-December (Box 23a, Folder 9)
    - 1905, January-July (Box 23b, Folder 1)
    - 1905, August-December (Box 23b, Folder 2)
    - 1906, January-February (Box 23b, Folder 3)
    - 1906, March-October (Box 23b, Folder 4)
    - 1906, Nov-December (Box 23b, Folder 5)
    - 1907, January-February (Box 23b, Folder 6)
    - 1907, March-April (Box 23b, Folder 7)
    - 1907, May-August (Box 23b, Folder 8)
    - 1907, September (Box 23b, Folder 9)
    - 1907, October-November (Box 23b, Folder 10)
    - 1907, December (Box 23b, Folder 11)
    - 1908, January-February (Box 23c, Folder 1)
    - 1908, March-May (Box 23c, Folder 2)
    - 1908, Oct-December (Box 23c, Folder 3)
    - 1909, January-April (Box 23c, Folder 4)
    - 1909, May-December (Box 23c, Folder 5)
    - 1910-1919 (Box 23c, Folder 6)
    - 1927-1943 (Box 23c, Folder 7)
    - Undated letters(2) (Box 23c, Folder 8)
    - Other papers
    - Invitation to Raoulwood, 25 May 1946 (Box 23c, Folder 9)
    - Tribute April 1953; Obituary and tribute, April 8 1953( photocopy) (Box 23c, Folder 10)
  - Rebecca Barnard Raoul papers, 1883-1930, Subseries 1.8; Personal name.; Box 24
    Rebecca Raoul was born on September 21, 1878 in Macon, Georgia. She was educated at various schools in New York and Atlanta, including the Washington Seminary. Following her debut in Atlanta (1897) and a tour of Europe (1899), she worked as volunteer district secretary of the Associated Charities of Atlanta and took active part in city social life. In 1908, Rebecca married Captain Frederick William Altstaetter of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. Three children were born to them, Mary Wadleigh (b. 1909), William Raoul (b. 1911), and Antonia (b. 1915). Between 1908 and 1918, the Altstaetter family lived in Wheeling, West Virginia, Washington, D.C., and Grand Rapids, Michigan. In 1918, they took up permanent residence in Savannah, where Rebecca was active in the League of Women Voters. She died on May 14, 1962.
    Letters from Rebecca Barnard Raoul, primarily to her mother and also to her sisters, date from 1883 to 1930. A few letters from her husband Frederick Altstaetter to his mother-in-law (1910-1919) are included. Many of Rebecca Raoul's letters were written during her frequent travels to Europe (1899 and 1903), Asheville and New York (1899-1900), Seattle (1902) and Japan (1905). On several occasions, she accompanied brother Tom on his search for a healthy climate. Letters from their trips West (1896-1897 and 1904) and their stay at a sanatorium in the Black Forest of Germany (1903) are included. Letters after 1908 from Wheeling, West Virginia.
    Rebecca's letters discuss family relationships, her brother's illness, social life in Atlanta, beaux, children and servants, travels, pregnancy and childbirth.
    - Letters of Rebecca Barnard Raoul
    - 1883-1898 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1899, January-July (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 1899, August-December (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 1900 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - 1902 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - 1903, April-July (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - 1903, August-November (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - 1904-1906 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - 1907-1910 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - 1911 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - 1912-1916 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - 1930 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Undated (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Letters of Frederick Altstaetter
    - 1910-1919 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Agnes Raoul papers, 1890-1914, Subseries 1.9; Personal name.; Box 25
    Agnes Raoul was born at Great Hill Place in Bolingbroke, Georgia on August 10, 1882. She attended Washington Seminary in Atlanta and Vassar College. After her Atlanta debut in 1901, she travelled in Europe in 1903 and returned to Atlanta to wed businessman Thomas Kearney Glenn in 1904. They were the parents of two sons, Wadley Raoul (b. 1905) and Wilbur Fisk (b. 1906). The Glenns were prominent members of Atlanta society and Agnes was active in establishing the Parent-Teacher Association in the city. She died of a brain tumor on November 3, 1914.
    The early letters of Agnes Raoul report on school, family activities, and Agnes's visits to brother Tom in Asheville and sister Mary in Washington, D.C. and Willet's Point, Long Island. Most of the letters were written from Vassar College, where Agnes was a student from 1899 to 1901. These letters detail her early impressions of the college, her activities as president of the freshman class, and various school rituals and student pastimes. In later letters she discussed her debut, her trip to Europe, and plans for her wedding to Tom Glenn. After her marriage, letters recount news of her children and in-laws, daily events, and occasional trips. A few school compositions (1891-1892) complete the subseries.
    - Letters, 1890-1914
    - 1890-1895 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1898 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - 1899, April-July (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 1899, August-September (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - 1899, October-December (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 1900, January-February (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - 1900, March-July (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - 1900, August-September (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - 1903-1907 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - 1909-1911 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Undated (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Other papers
    - School compositions, 1891-1892 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Rosine Raoul papers, 1892-1918, Subseries 1.10; Personal name.; Boxes 26-28
    Born on January 8, 1885 in Savannah, Rosine Raoul was educated at Washington Seminary in Atlanta and at Pratt Institute and the Veltin School in New York City, where she studied art. She made her debut in Atlanta in about 1904 and for the several years thereafter maintained an active social life in that city, often taking part in theater productions. In 1909, Rosine became ill with tuberculosis. Her next six years were spent primarily at sanatoriums in the Black Forest of Germany, Asheville, North Carolina, and Loomis, New York. From 1915 to 1918, she resided in Highlands, North Carolina. She died November 22, 1918 in Atlanta. Rosine Raoul was a published poet, essayist, and illustrator.
    Rosine Raoul's papers consist primarily of letters to her family from 1892 until her death in 1918. These letters, which bulk between 1898 and 1912, are mainly to her mother. The subseries also contains letters from friends, memorabilia, and samples of her drawings, poetry, and other writings.
    Rosine's earliest letters describe visits to Great Hill Place, Washington, D.C., Mexico, and Asheville (1892-1900); her brief enrollment at the Pratt Institute in New York (1899); and her years at the Veltin School in New York (1901-1903). Letters from 1904 to 1908 describe her active social life, courtships, travels, and art classes. Her letters from Arizona in 1906 and Germany in 1908 concern the poor health of brother Tom with whom she was travelling. Her own ill health, including a breakdown, is the subject of letters between 1906 and 1908.
    Rosine Raoul's letters from 1909 to 1918 document her losing battle with the "White Plague," tuberculosis. The letters from Germany detail the symptoms of her disease and the treatment she received at two Black Forest sanatoriums, Reiboldsgrun and Wehrawald. From 1910 to 1911, she wrote from Asheville, primarily from St. Joseph's Sanitarium, while other letters describe her stay at the Loomis Sanatorium in New York from 1911 to 1912.
    The writings of Rosine Raoul include her poetry notebook (1907-1908), and other poems, some of which appear in their published versions. Several were written during her stay at St. Joseph's and Loomis sanatoriums. Also included are short stories, reviews, other articles, and a play (1896). An additional article by Rosine on suffrage is filed in Subseries 1.12, papers of Eleonore Raoul (box 33, folder 1).
    - Letters, 1892-1918
    - 1892-1897 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1898 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 1899, June-September (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - 1899, October-November (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 1900 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - 1901 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - 1902, January-April (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - 1902, May-December (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - 1903, January-February (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - 1903, March-November (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - 1904, February-June (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - 1904, July-November (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - 1905 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - 1906, January-February (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - 1906, March-May (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - 1906, September-November (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - 1907 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - 1908, May-September (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - 1908, October-December (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - 1909, January-February (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - 1909, March-April (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - 1909, May-June (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - 1909, July-September (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - 1910, February-May (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - 1910, August-October (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - 1910, November-December (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - 1911, January -February (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - 1911, March-April (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - 1911, July-December (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - 1912 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - 1913-1918 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Undated (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Letters from various persons, 1902-1918 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Other papers
    - Poetry notebook, 1907-1908 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Poems (Box 28, Folder 2-5)
    - Writings (Box 28, Folder 6-8)
    - Drawings (Box 28, Folder 9-10)
    - The Veltin School - memorabilia (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Loring Raoul papers, 1895-1957, Subseries 1.11; Personal name.; Box 29
    Loring Raoul was born in Savannah on August 7, 1887. He attended the Peacock School in Atlanta and the Woodberry Forest School in Orange, Virginia before enrolling at the University of Georgia in 1904. After graduation in 1907, Loring held a variety of jobs in Chattanooga, Atlanta, and Asheville. In 1910, he established a chicken and egg business, "Cherokee Farms," in Smyrna, Georgia. Following his service with the army in France during World War I, Loring spent four years as production manager of the Tennessee Furniture Corporation in Chattanooga. After a brief residence in Scarsdale, New York, he settled in Sarasota, Florida, where he maintained a large farming enterprise. He was married in 1913 to Mary Courtenay Harrison, daughter of Col. Z. D. Harrison of "Fernbank" in Atlanta. They had three children, Harrison (b. 1914), Mary Wadliegh (b. 1919), and Loring (b. 1924). He died in Sarasota in November 1976.
    Most of Loring Raoul's letters date between 1902 and 1910 while he was attending preparatory school and college. Nearly all are to his mother, with a few to his sister Eleonore. Weekly letters from the Woodberry Forest School discuss lessons and examinations, football, track and field events, and the progress of brother Norman, who also attended Woodberry Forest (1902-1904). Between 1904 and 1907, Loring's letters describe college activities at the University of Georgia. Other letters are from Chattanooga, where he worked for brother Gaston at the Odorless Refrigerator Company (1907-1908), and from Asheville, where he worked in the office and on the grounds of the Manor (1909-1910). Later letters document his study of dairy farming in the Midwest (1910) and his military service at Camp Dix in New York during World War 1 (1918).
    - Letters, 1895-1957
    - 1895-1901 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - 1902 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - 1903, January-March (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - 1903, April-June (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - 1903, September-December (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - 1904, January-March (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - 1904, May-December (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - 1905 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - 1906, January-June (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - 1906, July-December (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - 1907 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - 1908 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - 1909, January-April (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - 1909, May-December (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - 1910 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - 1911-1918 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - 1946-1957 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Undated (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Eleonore Raoul papers, 1894-1982, Subseries 1.12; Personal name.; Boxes 30-34; OP 1-2
    Eleonore Raoul was born November 13, 1888 on Staten Island in New York. She received her early education at Washington Seminary in Atlanta, the Veltin School in New York City, and Saint Timothy's School near Baltimore. After her debut in Atlanta in 1907, Eleonore worked with the Associated Charities of Atlanta, took correspondence courses through the University of Chicago, and attended the Chicago School of Civics and Philanthropy in 1912.
    In 1915-1916, she served as organizer, press agent, and later as chairman of the Fulton and DeKalb Counties Branch of the Equal Suffrage Party of Georgia. She went on to work for a year with the National American Woman Suffrage Association as a field organizer in West Virginia and in the national offices of the Association in New York City. Returning to Atlanta in 1917, Eleonore enrolled in the Lamar School of Law at Emory University, and in 1920, became the first woman graduate of that school. Her brief law practice in Atlanta was interrupted the following year by a serious illness. During the early 1920's, Eleonore helped organize the Atlanta League of Women Voters and served as its president in 1922 and 1930. She remained active in Georgia League of Women Voters work throughout her life. She was the recipient of an honorary degree from Emory University in 1979. In 1928, Eleonore married Atlanta lawyer, Harry Letcher Greene. The couple adopted three children, Harry L., Jr. (b. 1931), Victoria (b. 1931), and Eleonore Raoul (b. 1935).
    Papers of Eleonore Raoul include correspondence, diaries, speeches, and other writings, subject files, clippings, and memorabilia. Also included are materials documenting her work with the woman's suffrage movement and the League of Women Voters in Georgia.
    Eleonore Raoul's letters to her friends and family date from 1895 to 1968, with the majority dating between 1906 and 1918. Many are to her mother, with others to her sister Rosine and daughter Lee. The early letters concern her activities at Saint Timothy's School (1905-1907), her extensive travels to visit relatives and friends (1907-1913), and her social and civic activities in Atlanta and Asheville (1909-1911). Letters from Chicago describe her work at a settlement house, her exposure to Socialism and union sentiments, and her attendance at lectures by Jane Addams and Bill Haywood (1912). Other letters concern her visits to Asheville (1910) and Loomis, New York (1912), to take care of sister Rosine.
    Between 1915 and 1917, most of Eleonore's letters concern her work with the woman's suffrage movement. She wrote Rosine about her travels and fundraising efforts for the Equal Suffrage Party in Georgia (1915-1916) and discussed her ideological differences with the Party leadership. Lengthy letters to her mother and Rosine during her service as a suffrage field worker in West Virginia for the National American Woman Suffrage Association describe speaking engagements, fund-raising, street meetings, door-to-door work and other activities (April-November 1916). She also discussed her low salary, long hours, lack of progress of the movement in West Virginia, and problems with her supervisors in the National Association. From December 1916 to March 1917, she wrote from the Association's headquarters in New York, where she was hired by Carrie Chapman Catt for general clerical work. Eleonore's later letters include several to sister Rebecca attempting to resolve an old quarrel (1930) and a number to daughter Lee at boarding school (1949-1954).
    The incoming letters are from friends and relatives, including several from husband Harry L. Greene and son Hal. There are letters of congratulations on her marriage (1928), and letters regarding her support of French war orphans (1931), her house and property in Highlands, North Carolina and Wadley family genealogy (1938), and sister Mary's last illness (1957-1958). Eleonore's diary (1921-1923) contains brief entries describing her attempts to establish a law practice in Atlanta, her involvement with the League of Women Voters, social events, and her serious illness during the latter half of 1922. The subject files concern activities with civic organizations to improve local government, her service on the boards of Fernbank, Inc. and the Fernbank Forest Association, and other topics.
    Eleonore Raoul's suffrage materials include correspondence, printed materials, clippings, posters, and scattered issues of suffrage journals. The correspondence relates to the Equal Suffrage Party of Georgia (1915), Eleonore's resignation as chairman of Fulton and DeKalb Counties Branch of the Party (1916), her work in West Virginia and New York with the National Association (1916-1917), and activities of the National Woman's Party (1917-1918). Correspondents include Carrie Chapman Catt and Alice Paul. Miscellaneous materials relating to the suffrage movement in Georgia include a description of the Atlanta suffrage parade of 1915, items concerning the attempt to merge the Georgia Woman's Suffrage Association and the Equal Suffrage Party of Georgia, and brief reminiscences by Eleonore Raoul about her involvement with the Equal Suffrage Party. One item of particular interest is the "Woman's Journal and Suffrage News Traveling Kampaign Kit" (ca. 70 pages), containing instructions on how to handle fund-raising, publicity, exhibits, meetings, and programs, and providing methods for rebutting anti-suffrage arguments.
    The League of Women Voters papers document Eleonore Raoul's involvement with three League organizations - the Atlanta, DeKalb County, and Georgia Leagues. The earliest materials concern the infant Atlanta League of Women Voters during the period of Eleonore's presidency in 1922. Included is a small amount of correspondence, items regarding the League-conducted Charter Campaign (an attempt to give Atlanta a city manager form of government), and the records of the League treasurer, Mrs. W. W. Lotspeich. A few Atlanta League materials of a later date are also present, including Eleonore's reminiscences on the history of the League. The DeKalb County League materials (1946-1959) include Eleonore's file from her service as co-chairman of the 1948 Finance Drive. The Georgia League of Women Voters materials (1946-1958) relate primarily to Eleonore's activities (1946-1948) as chairman of the Organization Committee (renamed the Extension Committee in 1948). Included are correspondence between state officers and individuals in local districts concerning the development of new chapters, reports on the work of the Extension Committee, and radio scripts used for promoting the League and its aims in Georgia.
    - Letters, 1895-1968
    - 1895-1905 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - 1906, February-June (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - 1906, October-December (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - 1907, January-April (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - 1907, May-August (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - 1908 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - 1909, January-February (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - 1909, March-November (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - 1910, January-August (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - 1910, September-December (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - 1911 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - 1912 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - 1913-1915 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - 1916, March-June (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - 1916, July (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - 1916, August-October (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - 1916, November-December (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - 1917-1918 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - 1919-1968 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Undated (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence and writings
    - Letters from various persons, 1894-1928 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Letters from various persons, 1930-1939 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Letters from various persons, 1940-1961 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Letters from various persons, 1963-1982 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Letters from various persons, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence re Mary Raoul Millis, 1957 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence re Mary Raoul Millis, 1958 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Greene family correspondence, 1948-1981 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Diary, 1921-1923 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Journal, 1953, July - "Notes on English Trip" (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Weekly notes, 1970, January-March (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Speeches and writings (Box 31, Folder 12-13)
    - Subject files and miscellaneous
    - Active voters - Miscellaneous, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Chicken business - Correspondence and records, 1942-1943 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Citizens' One Government League - Miscellaneous, ca. 1939-1941 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Fernbank - Correspondence, 1941-1949 (Box 32, Folder 4-5)
    - Fernbank - Minutes, reports, etc., 1939-1949 and undated (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
    - Fernbank - Printed material and clippings (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Highlands (N.C.) Consolidated School - Correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Horoscope - Correspondence and charts, 1919 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Local government - Miscellaneous (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Clippings re Eleonore Raoul, 1927-1981 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Memorabilia (Box 32, Folder 13)